so in
one on one recent occasion you said
you said
I might be paraphrasing slightly but you
said basically just purify each and every
basically just purify each and every
thought and it's arising don't do
anything on wholesome
the slightest and awesome thing and
that's the practice um um
and then
so that's kind of one brief description
of what the practice is
and then another kind of
description of what the practice is
that has also come up off on other
occasions is that the practice basically
constitutes consists of developing complete
consists of developing complete
understanding of the nature of things or
like completely undoing every
misunderstanding as we could say about
the nature of things
all right so the question is not like is
in regards to how to understand what the
practice is so like I think the question
that could be asked about this is are
these actually two like describing two
different things
or is it actually a description of the
exact same thing from
two slightly different perspectives because
because
sort of like for example
um that kind of previous type of view
that I used to have was much
well seemingly much closer to the first
of those things that I mentioned like
just don't do anything on wholesome and
then but I didn't occur to me and I
thought okay the one who has just
purified everything will understand will
have full knowledge and understanding by
virtue of his purification
but it didn't occur to me this
yes or that I could
or that I could
actually directly develop or try to
understand the nature of things and that
this could actually also constitute
purification in other words yeah well it's it's in
in other words yeah well it's it's in
what way are those two things related
yeah so
so
like the first thing you said
um yeah it's kind of true but you
realize then
that you don't know what purification is
and knowing what purification is it's
already a form of you or right view or
close to the right view so that that and
the views but then to the second thing
you said so they are
um they are mutually dependent
so you will not purify your views for as
long as you're behave in a purified
it simply won't happen but you won't
even start purifying your behavior for
as long as you views are not upgraded
so
that's why it's a bit of both in a way
because a person first needs to know
what to emphasize
eye behavior and I'm doing and learning
what's unwholesome and not doing
anything and then to emphasizing that all the
and then to emphasizing that all the
other views and misconceptions that they
might have by not emphasizing them and
by emphasizing Behavior they will be
purified and and that's like the faith aspect to
and and that's like the faith aspect to
some extent so you don't have to go and
figure out all of your misconceptions
you just have to figure out the the
fundamental the root ones that are
taking you away from emphasizing the
right thing such as purification and
what purification is
and see the example you gave like you
used to thought oh I just need to purify
everything I bet that meant I need to
stop having these thoughts and not have
them arise and always counter them and
always be there ready on points whenever
this happens I'll deal with this and
that's our purification yeah exactly
that is very strong so
that's why it's kind of a bit of both
because yes if somebody is truly
authentic they will understand the first
thing you said
and they won't misconceive it but most
people are not
and the first thing you said it's much
more easier to misconceive oh yeah on
hold some shoes I'll just be a good
person and I don't need to worry about
any of the doubts any of the views any
of the other things that are kind of um
then my existence revolves around
there's a no you do need to because you
don't know what purification is so yes
you got the idea okay I'll just purify
wholesome and and I'll I'll just purify
everything myself from a wholesome it
won't do anything that's rooted in greed
or aversion delusion it's like yeah but
do you know the extent of that and do
you know what purification is is it not
having thoughts of creative resolution
or is it not acting out of thoughts that
are pressuring you that's already
something that person needs to
repeatedly learn and relearn to
recognize that where that threshold of
their responsibility is as we keep
saying you know you have to endure
things rightly and so on and then these
things can become apparent
um so and all that would be known on
account of operating reviews when I
can't do reflecting rightly pondering uh
Discerning contemplating and then the
first part that you need to do becomes
clearer now of course if all you do is just
now of course if all you do is just
Chase around things that are unclear and
try to kind of assuage your own doubt
all the time and ignore the emphasis on
the purification of behavior the speech
and thoughts well then
you won't purify your thoughts okay you
might have them theoretically all lined
up perfectly but your behavior is still
carrying the fuel for the wrong views
and that's that the relay chariot so the
views are purified on account of
behavior on a kind of virtue that leads
to the development of Somali that then
leads to the purification of you the eye
dropping all the all the wrong views
yeah yeah so today
yeah so today
emphasizing The Virtue and samadhi that
comes out of it rightly
like being able to to endure the
pressure of centrality or will not act
out of it seeds full extent to learn how
not to be moved by it
like back in the day somebody could have
done that on account of faith alone the
Buddha would tell them and they wouldn't
need they would not pay attention to any
doubts that they have they would just
stick to it today it's highly unlikely
so you would need to really clarify why
this is so but then you have to start
doing it
you have to start enduring it
yeah I was also thinking that there's
I was also thinking that there's
um
like a kind of corollary to that aspect
of this is
also the fact that for example it might
be said that
you've just develop understanding of the
nature of the sense spaces for example
nature of I ear
so like if you genuinely want to try and
understand the nature of what is what is
your eye for example or what is what's
the Matrix interface is what are they
impermanent what does that even mean
like to develop practical understanding
of that
it becomes quite clear quite quickly
that it's completely incompatible like
on you know throughout the day at having
this as a kind of a contemplation it's
completely incompatible with acting out
of your senses as in just distracting
yeah like you know I mean if you're if
you're honestly genuinely trying to
understand that thing
it naturally kind of pertains to
something that
is
yeah kind of incompatible with the
attitude of greed and aversion and
delusion so in that sense as well
it could be said that
um like correctly developing an
understanding of things has to it kind
of naturally comes to include
a degree of purification there aren't
things that have never thought about
steppers or almost never are and that's
also like a different characters
different people different faculties
will come into into play the um
somebody might naturally have more
more of a kind of affinity towards that
you know mental Clarity contemplation
reflection approach but yeah even they
if they're honest they will recognize
well there is nothing to me there's
nothing for me to apply this this
approach and reflection unless my
behavior is being purified
unless virtue and sense restraint is my
mode of being
uh somebody one might be like less
reflective less doubtful less inclined
to think about these things but then
they would
uh see them in Broad Strokes on account
of doing the work of purification and
Somalian or in composure
so whichever whichever one you put sort
of forward as as your way of engaging
with with towards getting understanding
the other one will have to follow but
fundamentally yeah
um the order of development is like you
need to have had virtue established for
quite a while
sense restraint to be able to contain
that pressure see it not act out of it
and then whichever aspect of practice
your inclinations might put first well
it can come to some sort of fruition
because as I said you have contained it
and that's the again the the order of
the gradual training yeah so that
doesn't mean that like Okay so until I'm
developed in virtue I should not think
or read any suta well that's silly
because that's already a view you don't
start with neutral views you start with
lots of views so yeah read the sentence
and stuff just don't forget what comes
first and what holds it underneath what
type of development and there is a
compromise there
what in regard to you know I don't know
five Aggregates or something but you
don't doubt that precepts come first in
a sense restraint and guarding of the
doors and doors and watchfulness and so
on
um so it's and through doing that
your views are being clarified
and through clarifying your views
keeping the precepts and during the
pressure not being moved on account of
it will become easier because because
it's It just fits it makes more sense
you're not you're not resisting that
idea anymore it's not bothering you as
much hmm I was thinking like
hmm I was thinking like
it's just one of the reasons I was
thinking about this was just like if you
read nanavira for example
he almost never talks or mentions
explicitly you know sensor strange and
virtue and so on and he's all about
really understanding
and you know one could kind of then
mistakenly get the impression for from
that that oh well that's kind of all he
was doing but at the same if you really
read it properly it's very obvious that
none of the
he's able to describe the very subtlest
forms of bad faith on the level of the
tiniest view or thought that it's
obviously impossible that sure could be
seen or understood without all one needs
to do is just have a look and see how he
lived and exactly
he lives in you know quite a steer
remote area even today these days it's
quite um added in that area of Sri Lanka but
um added in that area of Sri Lanka but
back then it was even worse and and he
lived there uh 24 7 for years yeah so
that already takes commitment and
composure and so on so but yes as a as a
as a as an instruction
yeah if it is teaching you realize yeah
it can people can easily Overlook and
they do Overlook especially people with
intellectual Tendencies they tend to you
know really like like folks but Overlook
the entire aspect of their lifestyle
underneath everything that Nina Vera
thought and uh and Views he had and
teachings he conveyed so people will be
doing PhD in an Avira and stuff which is
like a quite a contradiction in terms
um but and he mentions in passing I
remember in some ways like that of
course the Virgin is interesting that's
they don't he doesn't even talk about it
in the book because you just take it for
granted that you have to do it yeah but
you realize when when people new people
are approaching it it's it's not it's
not necessarily wasteful to to mention
it and re-establish it as a necessary
basis because if you do establish it
then tenth of your effort into
understanding in the video and
clarifying all those ideas he had will
be more than enough for what you're
trying to achieve but if you're not
developed in virtue not sufficiently not
sufficiently restrained uh then you
could be you know revolving day and
night and still not really land on
anything that matters so to speak
because the bass is still not there that
the bad fuel is still is still there
being provided inadvertently to all the
views and misconceptions so in other
words all your effort is applied
theoretically yeah and it's over there
and then it can also then lead to
further worsening of your wrong views
where but now you think that you
understood both neither and the Buddha
while still even your basic virtue and
sense to strength and not acting out of
unwholesome mental States is not even
purified
it's a refreshing in a way the fact that
he kind of finds it so
obvious or takes it so much for granted
that the the types of lifestyle and The
Virtue that needs that he doesn't even
kind of feel the need to mention it but
it's totally implied to implicit in
everything that is said in other words
that it's like
it's like
kind of refreshing from the point of
view of
um you know there's so much
reviews and discussion over what
constitutes even even virtue and piano
you can think it's very virtuous and
it's all by by just merely kind of
living a lifestyle that is not even
close to even what he was living but
but for him it was just well like of
course I have to do that but that's not
even even close to enough because then
you still need to develop understanding
yes it's like Discerning that
fine middle line
between just
adhering to the prescribed sets of behavior on a
to the prescribed sets of behavior on a
kind of belief
that this is leading me closer to the
light of nibana
or just falling into that completely
just uh explanatory psychologizing
everything must be answered and fit
completely out of your mental craving
but you don't see that
um so descending the middle line would
be like yeah so if you are
protecting certain types of behavior
guiding your speech guarding your sense
those for the sake of
for the sake of
diminishing the views that you don't
necessarily need to hunt down one by one
you just need to stick to this behavior
and then keep an eye on the general
picture okay it's my mind now since I've been
okay it's my mind now since I've been
investing on every presets and during
the the pulls and the pressures of
unwholesome things not acting out of it
seeing the danger in them is my mind
calmer are things clearer when suffering
arises how long it possessed how strong
is the tendency for me to get rid of the
Arizona suffering where it arises is
that diminishing
am I am I more indifferent towards it am
I still afraid am I still bothered by it
do I still really crave for it to end
all of those little things already
showing you the development
and that's why if somebody is not
too concerned about answering you know
every permutation that a mind might come
up with
but instead protects behavior develops
this type of samadhi of learning how to
be movable in regard to things they want
to move you
and then yeah the craving is actually
diminishing you're not feeling it you're
not providing any more any more firewood
for it and then those those phenol
become obvious oh look my mind is not
moved anymore and now you see and now
you see exactly why and there is no more
doubt there
oh yeah the reasonable I don't crave
when unpleasant feeling touches it I
don't move either way so why would I
kick and scream internally to get rid of
it and replace it with pleasure when I
already developed the value of
immovability so you could see how this type of
so you could see how this type of
development through through this correct
money is
not as unpleasant
like either way you have to do the
pressure but how much you revolve around
it
how much will you you know be griped by
doubts and all the pain that comes with
it
that's that's not that's not going to be
there because you are emphasizing the
behavior and the immovability and Club
it in regard to that so you're able to
refrain your own self from oh but let me just
your own self from oh but let me just
think about it and provide you know and
clarified disability no no let me just
think about what's right here what's
right pressuring me what current state
of matter is that's the extent of my
thought not like well stop think about
it and I just do these things blindly
that will be again falling back onto
that I'm just mechanically doing this
Behavior expecting balance to happen no
no you need to let the pressure in to
some extent but then you also have a
choice how far you will then go on
account of it mentally
uh and that person can arrive with the
same goal without having to suffer much
internally when it comes to mental
turmoil and hindrances but doing the
work now the other person who also does
the work
and also would then be giving in to the
tendency to you know opportune different
aspects clarify compare it Revisited
see if he can doubt it bring up the
doubt just to see if it's gonna do all
these things well that's going to cause
more pain but of course he's factually
exploring more so although he will
suffer more
um he will have more
familiarity with various different
aspects of practice
fundamentally he will arrive at the same
goal and that's really the goal
it's not like how many facets of the
time are you you you are familiar with
it's are you fully free from free
division delusion or not
so that's for whether you arrive through
faith or through your just sticking to
the composure practice of allowing
pressure to come in but not revolving
around it too far
or are you the type who will revolve
around too far and then extend that
endurance to that level and suffer on
account of it
either way these three types whoever
arrives first at being another Hunt is
the best
that's it
because that's really the measure of
success
there's a there's actually a Suitor that
I
thought it might be relevant to this I
might it's in this
so what somebody is asking a question so
people say there are sages in the world
and how is that
do they call the one who qualifies
through knowledge as age or else the one
who qualifies through
virtue or behavior
and the answer is neither through view
nor through learning or knowledge do the
skillful ones call a sage here
those who are unopposing trouble free
and rid of Hope
who live like this these I call sages
yeah the extinguished ones yeah and
and
so then it's
continues he asks so these recluses and
brahmanas who declare Purity through the
scene and the herds who declare Purity
through virtue and practices declare
Purity in various other ways I wonder if
they are blessed one
uh living in accordance with that if
they have crossed birth in old age
and the answer is
um
basically that they have not crossed
birth in old age whoever took their
purity in any of these ways
um and the answer I'm kind of shortening
it because it's basically just
so if if these who have declared Purity
in all of these various ways and if you
say that they have not crossed the flood
then who has crossed worth an old age um
um
so the answer is I do not say that all
recluses and brahmins are in the grip of
birth and old age
those who have abandoned the scene the
herds thought as well as virtue and
practice and have abandoned various
other ways too who are fully known
craving and their tankers they indeed
are those who have crossed the floods so it's
so it's
yeah so that's the that's the suit but
that seemed to be kind of relating to us
saying a similar thing
a lot of these actually I find
they're they're kind of saying similar
things in other ways they always just
come back to this
very pertinent points that it's all comes
pertinent points that it's all comes
down to just abandoning craving
in whatever from whatever angle
particular angle it doesn't really
matter
but then obviously that needs to be
still understood what that actually
means
it reminds me in a way of the challenge
that we're talking about God when he
asks so is it through Purity through
virtue no because it's your
knowledgeable you know but it's not without it yeah